Dwight Lyman Moody Collection
Dwight Lyman Moody Collection
1876-1968
Moody, Dwight Lyman, 1837-1899.
1 linear ft.
American Protestant clergyman and evangelist. Collection contains correspondence, subject files, writings, photographs and research material.
3174712
Biographical History
Dwight Lyman Moody (1837-1899) was an American Protestant clergyman and evangelist.
Born in Northfield, Massachusetts, Moody settled in Chicago in 1856 where he became successful in business and active in reliogious work. He withdrew from business in 1861 to devote his full energies to city missionary work. During the Civil War he acted as agent of the United States Christian Commission and was also secretary of the YMCA.
In 1867, while in England, Moody carried on evangelistic work. In 1870 he became associated with Ira D. Sankey, organist and singer. Together they made two notable tours of England (1873-1875 and 1881-1883), and held meetings in many parts of the United States. Their collections of gospel hymns were well received.
In 1879 Moody established Northfield Seminary for Young Women, the first of a chain of educational institutions of his planning. Mount Hermon School for Young Men was added in 1881, and the Bible Institute for Home and Foreign Missions in 1889. He also inaugurated the Students' Conference and the Christian Workers' Conference in Northfield.
Moody was married to Emma C. Revell, with whom he had three children: Emma Moody Fitt, William Revell Moody, and Paul Dwight Moody, who became President of Middlebury College.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dwight Lyman Moody Collection consists of correspondence, subject files, writings, photographs and clippings. The collection is divided into two parts according to the donor.
Material donated by Mrs. E.M. Powell, grand-daughter of Mr. Moody, contains correspondence, subject files, writings and photographs. These are further subdivided as shown in the following shelf list. Subject files include ephemera and a curator's file. Writings consist of articles by and about Moody, including one page of a sermon outline in his handwriting. Photographs include several of Moody at various ages.
Material donated by Mr. Colton Storm contains material relating to Dwight Lyman Moody and material relating to Carl Sidney Bishop. The Moody material includes correspondence, clippings and a curator's file. The Bishop material contains correspondence and a Parsons family genealogy. Mr. Bishop was Mr. Storm's grandfather and a correspondence of Moody.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Related Material
has extensive holdings relating to church and clergy in Central New York. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Religion and philosophy; Bishop, Carl Sidney.; Moody, Dwight Lyman, 1837-1899.; Evangelists -- Great Britain.; Evangelists -- United States.; Protestant churches -- Clergy.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Genealogies (histories); Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. E.M. Powell.
Gift of Colton Storm.
Inventory
- E.M. Powell, donor
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1895; 1898,; 1899 (Box 1)
  - Subject files
    - Announcements, 1886 (Box 1)
    - Centenary celebration, 1937 (Box 1)
    - Curator's file, 1946-1968 (Box 1)
    - Genealogy (Box 1)
    - Sheet music, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - About Moody, 1936-1937; printed material (Box 1)
    - By Moody, 1900; manuscripts, printed material (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Birthplace (Box 1)
    - Burial place (Box 1)
    - Library (Box 1)
    - Mother (Box 1)
    - Plaque (Box 1)
    - Sankey, I.D. (Box 1)
    - Self, 1870-1879 (Box 1)
    - Son (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
- Colton Storm, donor
  - Dwight L. Moody material
    - Correspondence, 1891; 1894,; 1898-1899 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1899; funeral; meetings (Box 1)
    - Curator's file, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Carl Sidney Bishop material
    - Correspondence, 1903-1904; 1912,; 1915 (Box 1)
    - Genealogy, Parsons family, 1894; 1915 (Box 1)